# Thomas Shull

Hardstrasse 201 Floor 17, 8005 Zurich CH, email: mail@tomshull.com, mobile: +1-217-801-4613, thomasshull.net

Research Interests Hardware and software designs to improve the performance of managed languages. Development of new persistent programming frameworks. Virtual Machine modifications to utilize emerging byte-addressable persistent memory technologies. Profiling-based compiler optimizations. Techniques to reduce the overhead of automatic memory management.

EDUCATION

### University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2012 - August 2020

Ph.D. in Computer Science Advisor: Prof. Josep Torrellas

**Thesis**: Making Non-Volatile Memory Programmable

Committee: Prof. Josep Torrellas, Prof. Jian Huang, Prof. David Padua, Prof. James Larus,

and Prof. Steven Swanson

## Washington University of St. Louis

June 2008 - May 2012

B.Sc. in Computer Science and B.Sc. in Computer Engineering

Summa Cum Laude

Professional EXPERIENCE

## Oracle Labs Senior Researcher with GraalVM Team

June 2020 - Present

Working on performance improvements for Substrate VM (SVM) and enhancing the AArch64 port of GraalVM. SVM is a framework and runtime environment for the ahead-of-time compilation of Java applications and one component of GraalVM. GraalVM is a new compiler, runtime, and language development environment to improve both the developer experience and performance.

Arm Ltd.

July 2019 – April 2020

#### **Open Source Software**

Worked on AArch64 port of Substrate VM (SVM). Made multiple bug fixes and performance improvements, including adding support for AArch64 runtime code installation.

#### Non-Volatile Memory Research

Proposed ISA extensions to improve crash-consistent application performance by enabling more aggressive instruction reordering; implemented extensions within gem5 simulator. Also improved and fixed the AArch64 port of the Persistent Memory Development Kit.

SELECTED Publications Execution Dependence Extension (EDE): ISA Support for Eliminating Fences (ISCA 2021), Thomas Shull, Ilias Vougioukas, Nikos Nikoleris, Wendy Elsasser, and Josep Torrellas

AutoPersist: An Easy-To-Use Java NVM Framework Based on Reachability (PLDI 2019), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

Reusable Inline Caching for JavaScript Performance (PLDI 2019), Jiho Choi, Thomas Shull, and Josep Torrellas

QuickCheck: Using Speculation to Reduce the Overhead of Checks in NVM Frameworks (VEE 2019), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

NoMap: Speeding-Up JavaScript Using Hardware Transactional Memory (HPCA 2019), Thomas Shull, Jiho Choi, María J. Garzarán, and Josep Torrellas

Biased Reference Counting: Minimizing Atomic Operations in Garbage Collection (PACT 2018), Jiho Choi, **Thomas Shull**, and Josep Torrellas

Defining a High-level Programming Model for Emerging NVRAM Technologies (ManLang 2018), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

ShortCut: Architectural Support for Fast Object Access in Scripting Languages (ISCA 2017), Jiho Choi, **Thomas Shull**, and Josep Torrellas

Improving JavaScript Performance by Deconstructing the Type System (PLDI 2014), Wonsun Ahn, Jiho Choi, **Thomas Shull**, María J. Garzarán, and Josep Torrellas

TECHNICAL SKILLS Programming Skills: C/C++, Java, Python.

Managed Language Implementations: JavaScript-V8, JavaScriptCore; Swift; Java-HotSpot, Maxine, Substrate VM

Compiler Implementations: Graal, LLVM

References

Christian Wimmer, christian.wimmer@oracle.com Stuart Monteith, stuart.monteith@arm.com

Josep Torrella, torrella@illinois.edu

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Additional references available upon request

Oracle Labs

Arm Ltd.